I'd like to share with you
أود أن أشارككم
the story of one of my patients called Celine.
قصة إحدى مريضاتي تدعى سلين.
Celine is a housewife and lives in a rural district
سيلين ربة منزل تعيش في منطقة ريفية
of Cameroon in west Central Africa.
في الكاميرون في غرب أفريقيا الوسطى.
Six years ago, at the time of her HIV diagnosis,
منذ ست سنوات, عندما تم تشخيصها بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية,
she was recruited to participate in the clinical trial
كانت قد عينت للمشاركة في التجربة الإكلينيكية
which was running in her health district at the time.
التي كانت تجري في الوحدة الصحية الخاصة بالمنطقة التي تسكنها في ذلك الوقت.
When I first met Celine, a little over a year ago,
عندما قابلت سيلين للمرة الأولى, منذ ما يزيد قليلا عن سنة,
she had gone for 18 months
كانت قد أمضت 18 شهرًا
without any antiretroviral therapy,
بدون أي علاج مضاد للفيروسات الارتدادية,
and she was very ill.
وكانت مريضة جدًا.
She told me that she stopped coming to the clinic
قالت لي أنها توقفت عن القدوم للعيادة
when the trial ended
عندما انتهت التجربة
because she had no money for the bus fare
لأنها لم يكن لديها نقود لتدفع أجرة الحافلة
and was too ill to walk the 35-kilometer distance.
ولأنها كانت مريضة جدًا لتسير مسافة ال35 كيلومتر.
Now during the clinical trial,
خلال التجربة الإكلينيكية,
she'd been given all her antiretroviral drugs free of charge,
كان يتم إعطائها جميع أدويتها بالمجان,
and her transportation costs
وكان يتم تغطية مصاريف تنقلها
had been covered by the research funds.
من قبل صندوق رأس مال البحث.
All of these ended once the trial was completed,
كل هذا انتهى باكتمال التجربة,
leaving Celine with no alternatives.
تاركًا سيلين بلا بدائل.
She was unable to tell me the names of the drugs
لم تستطع أن تخبرني بأسماء الأدوية
she'd received during the trial,
التي تلقتها خلال التجربة,
or even what the trial had been about.
أو حتى عن ماذا كانت تدور التجربة.
I didn't bother to ask her what the results of the trial were
لم أكلف نفسي بسؤالها عن نتائج التجربة,
because it seemed obvious to me that she would have no clue.
لأنه بدا لي واضحًا أنها لم تكن لتعرف الإجابة.
Yet what puzzled me most
بالرغم من ذلك أكثر ما حيرني
was Celine had given her informed consent
كان موافقة سيلين
to be a part of this trial, yet she clearly did not understand
على أن تكون جزء من هذه التجربة, بالرغم من أنه كان واضحًا أنها لم تدرك
the implications of being a participant
آثار كونها مشتركة في التجربة
or what would happen to her once the trial had been completed.
أو ما الذي يمكن أن يحدث لها عند انتهاء التجربة.
Now, I have shared this story with you as an example
الآن, لقد شاركتكم هذه القصة لتكون مثالًا
of what can happen to participants in the clinical trial
لما يمكن أن يحدث للمشتركين في التجربة الإكلينيكية
when it is poorly conducted.
عندما يتم تنفيذها بصورة سيئة.
Maybe this particular trial yielded exciting results.
من الممكن أن تكون هذه التجربة تحديدًا قد أثمرت نتائج مثيرة.
Maybe it even got published in a high-profile scientific journal.
من الممكن حتى أن تكون نشرت في مجلة علمية رائدة.
Maybe it would inform clinicians around the world
من الممكن أنها ستعلم أطباء من حول العالم
on how to improve on the clinical management of HIV patients.
عن كيفية تحسين المعلاجة الإكلينيكية لمرضى فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية.
But it would have done so at a price
لكنها ستفعل ذلك على حساب
to hundreds of patients who, like Celine,
الكثير من المرضى الذين, مثل سيلين
were left to their own devices
قد تركوا لحالهم
once the research had been completed.
عندما انتهت التجربة.
I do not stand here today to suggest in any way
أنا لا أقف هنا اليوم لأوحي بأي حال من الأحوال
that conducting HIV clinical trials
أن إجراء التجارب الإكلينيكية لمرضى فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
in developing countries is bad.
في البلاد النامية هو شيء سيء.
On the contrary, clinical trials are extremely useful tools,
بل على العكس, التجارب الإكلينيكية تعد أدوات مفيدة جدًا,
and are much needed to address the burden
ولازمة جدًا لمواجهة عبء
of disease in developing countries.
المرض في البلدان النامية.
However, the inequalities that exist between
على الرغم من ذلك, التفاوت الحاصل بين
richer countries and developing countries in terms of funding
البلاد الأغنى والبلدان النامية من حيث التمويل
pose a real risk for exploitation,
يشكل خطر حقيقي للاستغلال,
especially in the context of externally-funded research.
خاصة في سياق البحث الممول من الخارج.
Sadly enough, the fact remains that
بكل حزن, تبقى حقيقة أن
a lot of the studies that are conducted in developing countries
الكثير من الدراسات التي تجرى في البلدان النامية
could never be authorized in the richer countries
لا يمكن أن يرخص بها في البلدان الأغنى
which fund the research.
التي تمول البحث.
I'm sure you must be asking yourselves
أنا متأكدة أنكم تسألون أنفسكم
what makes developing countries,
ما الذي يجعل البلدان النامية,
especially those in sub-Saharan Africa,
خاصةً تلك الواقعة في جنوب الصحراء الإفريقية الكبرى,
so attractive for these HIV clinical trials?
جذابة جدًا للتجارب الإكلينيكية المتعلقة بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية ؟
Well, in order for a clinical trial to generate
في الحقيقة, لتنتج التجربة الإكلينيكية
valid and widely applicable results,
نتائج صالحة وقابلة للتطبيق على نحو واسع,
they need to be conducted with large numbers of study participants
يجب أن تطبق على عدد كبير من المشاركين
and preferably on a population
ويفضل لو كانوا من عينة
with a high incidence of new HIV infections.
لديها نسبة كبيرة من الإصابات الجديدة بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية.
Sub-Saharan Africa largely fits this description,
إفريقيا جنوب الصحراء الكبرى تلائم هذا الوصف إلى حد كبير,
with 22 million people living with HIV,
بها 22 مليون شخص متعايش مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشري,
an estimated 70 percent of the 30 million people
حوالي 70 بالمئة من ال30 مليون شخص
who are infected worldwide.
المصاب بالعالم.
Also, research within the continent
كما أن إجراء البحث العلمي داخل قارة إفريقيا
is a lot easier to conduct due to widespread poverty,
يعد أسهل كثيرًا وذلك لاستشراء الفقر
endemic diseases and inadequate health care systems.
والأمراض المزمنة وقلة كفاءة نظم الرعاية الصحية.
A clinical trial that is considered to be
التجربة الإكلينيكية
potentially beneficial to the population
التي من الممكن أن تشكل إفادة للشعب
is more likely to be authorized,
على الأرجح سيتم التصريح بها,
and in the absence of good health care systems,
وفي غياب نظم الرعاية الصحية الجيدة,
almost any offer of medical assistance
يصبح أي عرض للمساعدة الطبية
is accepted as better than nothing.
مقبولًا لأنه أحسن من لا شيء.
Even more problematic reasons include
وحتى الأسباب المستعصية أكثر تتضمن
lower risk of litigation,
خطر أقل الدعاوى القضائية
less rigorous ethical reviews,
ومراجعات أخلاقية أقل صرامة
and populations that are willing to participate
والناس المستعدين للمشاركة
in almost any study that hints at a cure.
في أي دراسة تلمح لوجود شفاء.
As funding for HIV research
وكلما ازداد التمويل لأبحاث فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
increases in developing countries
في البلدان النامية
and ethical review in richer countries become more strict,
وازدادت صرامة المراجعة الأخلاقية في البلدان الأغنى,
you can see why this context becomes
بإمكانك أن تدرك لماذا يصبح هذا السياق
very, very attractive.
جذاب جدًا جدًا.
The high prevalence of HIV drives researchers
نسبة الانتشار الكبيرة لفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية يسوق الباحثين
to conduct research that is sometimes scientifically acceptable
لإجراء بحث من الممكن أن يكون مقبول علميًا
but on many levels ethically questionable.
لكنه مشكك فيه أخلاقيًا بمستويات كثيرة.
How then can we ensure that, in our search for the cure,
إذن, كيف يمكننا التأكد, من أننا خلال بحثنا عن العلاج,
we do not take an unfair advantage
لا نقوم باستغلال
of those who are already most affected by the pandemic?
المتضررين من هذا الوباء؟
I invite you to consider four areas I think we can focus on
أدعوكم للتركيز على أربع نقاط
in order to improve the way in which things are done.
من أجل تحسين الطريقة التي تتم بها الأمور.
The first of these is informed consent.
أولا إفادة الموافقة.
Now, in order for a clinical trial to be
الآن, حتى تعد التجربة الإكلينيكية
considered ethically acceptable,
مقبولة أخلاقيًا,
participants must be given the relevant information
يجب أن يتم إعطاء المشاركين كافة المعلومات ذات الصلة بالبحث
in a way in which they can understand,
بطريقة يستطيعون فهمها,
and must freely consent to participate in the trial.
ويجب عليهم اختيار قبول المشاركة في التجربة.
This is especially important in developing countries,
هذه النقطة مهمة جدًا خاصةً في البلدان النامية,
where a lot of participants consent to research
حيث يتجه كثير من المشاركين لإبداء قبولهم مشاركتهم في البحث
because they believe it is the only way in which
لاعتقادهم أن هذا هو الطريق الوحيد
they can receive medical care or other benefits.
لتلقي الرعاية الطبية أو أي فوائد أخرى.
Consent procedures that are used in richer countries
إجراءات الموافقة التي تتم في البلدان الأغنى
are often inappropriate or ineffective
تكون في الغالب غير ملائمة أو غير فعالة
in a lot of developing countries.
في الكثير من البلدان النامية.
For example, it is counterintuitive to have
مثال على ذلك, هو شيء مغاير للمنطق أن تجعل
an illiterate study participant, like Celine,
شخص أمي مشارك في التجربة, مثل سيلين,
sign a lengthy consent form that they are unable to read,
يوقع بالموافقة على عقد طويل لا يستطيع قرائته,
let alone understand.
فضلا عن فهمه.
Local communities need to be more involved
يجب على المجتمعات المحلية أن تشارك أكثر
in establishing the criteria for recruiting participants
في ترسيخ معايير اختيار المشاركين
in clinical trials, as well as the incentives for participation.
في التجارب الإكلينيكية, إضافة إلى حوافز المشاركة.
The information in these trials
المعلومات في هذه التجارب
needs to be given to the potential participants
يجب أن يتم الإدلاء بها للمشاركين المحتملين
in linguistically and culturally acceptable formats.
بأسلوب مناسب لغويًا وثقافيًا.
The second point I would like for you to consider
النقطة الثانية التي أود منكم أخذها بعين الاعتبار
is the standard of care that is provided
هو مستوى الرعاية التي تتوفر
to participants within any clinical trial.
للمشاركين في أي تجربة إكلينيكية.
Now, this is subject to a lot of debate and controversy.
هذا موضوع معرض للكثير من الجدال والمناقشات.
Should the control group in the clinical trial
هل يجب إعطاء المجموعة المرجعية في التجربة الإكلينيكية
be given the best current treatment which is available
أفضل علاج حالي متوفر
anywhere in the world?
في أي مكان بالعالم؟
Or should they be given an alternative standard of care,
أم يجب توفير مستوى رعاية بديل لهم,
such as the best current treatment available
كأفضل علاج متوفر حاليًا
in the country in which the research is being conducted?
داخل البلد التي يتم فيها البحث؟
Is it fair to evaluate a treatment regimen
هل من العدل تقييم نظام علاجي
which may not be affordable or accessible
من الممكن ألا يكون متوفرًا
to the study participants once the research has been completed?
للمشاركين في الدراسة حالما يكتمل البحث؟
Now, in a situation where the best current treatment
الآن, حين يكون العلاج الحالي الأمثل
is inexpensive and simple to deliver,
غير مكلف ويمكن إيصاله بسهولة,
the answer is straightforward.
فالإجابة معروفة.
However, the best current treatment available
لكن, العلاج الحالي الأمثل المتوفر
anywhere in the world is often very difficult
في أي مكان بالعالم, غالبا ما يكون توفيره
to provide in developing countries.
في البلدان النامية صعبا جدًا.
It is important to assess the potential risks and benefits
من المهم تقييم المخاطر والمصالح المحتملة
of the standard of care which is to be provided
لمستوى الرعاية الذي سيوفر
to participants in any clinical trial,
للمشاركين في أي تجربة إكلينيكية,
and establish one which is relevant for the context of the study
وتأسيس مستوى رعاية يكون ذو صلة بسياق البحث
and most beneficial for the participants within the study.
ويكون الأكثر إفادة للمشاركين في البحث.
That brings us to the third point I want you think about:
يحضرنا هذا للنقطة الثالثة التي أريدكم أن تفكروا بها:
the ethical review of research.
المراجعة الأخلاقية للبحث.
An effective system for reviewing the ethical suitability
وجود نظام فعال لمراجعة الجدارة الأخلاقية
of clinical trials is primordial to safeguard participants
للتجارب الإكلينيكية هو شيء أساسي لحماية المشاركين
within any clinical trial.
في أي تجربة إكلينيكية.
Unfortunately, this is often lacking
لسوء الحظ, غالبًا ما يغيب هذا النظام
or inefficient in a lot of developing countries.
أو يكون غير فعال في كثير من البلدان النامية.
Local governments need to set up effective systems
الحكومات المحلية يجب أن تؤسس نظم فعالة
for reviewing the ethical issues around the clinical trials
لمراجعة المسائل الأخلاقية المتعلقة بالتجارب الإكلينيكية
which are authorized in different developing countries,
التي يتم التصريح بها في مختلف البلدان النامية,
and they need to do this by setting up
وعليهم فعل ذلك من خلال تأسيس
ethical review committees that are independent
لجان مراجعة أخلاقية مستقلة
of the government and research sponsors.
عن الحكومة وعن ممولي البحث.
Public accountability needs to be promoted
يجب أن يتم تعزيز فكرة المسئولية العامة
through transparency and independent review
عن طريق الشفافية والمراجعة المستقلة
by nongovernmental and international organizations
من طرف المنظمات الغير الحكومية والعالمية
as appropriate.
حسب الاقتضاء.
The final point I would like for you to consider tonight
النقطة الأخيرة التي أود منكم أخذها بعين الاعتبار الليلة
is what happens to participants in the clinical trial
هي ماذا يحدث للمشاركين في التجربة الإكلينيكية
once the research has been completed.
عند انتهاء البحث.
I think it is absolutely wrong for research to begin
أعتقد أن من الخطأ الأكيد بدء البحث
in the first place without a clear plan
في المقام الأول بدون وجود خطة واضحة
for what would happen to the participants
لما يمكن أن يحدث للمشاركين
once the trial has ended.
مع انتهاء التجربة.
Now, researchers need to make every effort to ensure that
الآن, على الباحثين أن يبذلوا كل جهد لضمان
an intervention that has been shown to be beneficial
أي تدخل بدا أنه مفيد
during a clinical trial
خلال التجربة الإكلينيكية
is accessible to the participants of the trial
أن يكون متوفراً للمشاركين في التجربة
once the trial has been completed.
عند انتهائها.
In addition, they should be able to consider the possibility
إضافة لذلك, عليهم الأخذ بالاعتبار إمكانية
of introducing and maintaining effective treatments
تقديم العلاجات الفعالة والمحافظة على هذا التقديم
in the wider community once the trial ends.
في المجتمع الأوسع مع انتهاء التجربة.
If, for any reason, they feel that this might not be possible,
لو لأي سبب من الأسباب شعروا أن هذا لن يكون ممكنًا,
then I think they should have to ethically justify
فأعتقد أن عليهم أن يقدموا التبرير الأخلاقي
why the clinical trial should be conducted in the first place.
لسبب القيام بالتجربة بالمقام الأول.
Now, fortunately for Celine,
الآن, لحسن حظ سيلين,
our meeting did not end in my office.
لم ينتهي لقائنا بمكتبي.
I was able to get her enrolled into a free HIV treatment program
استطعت أن ألحقها ببرنامج مجاني لمعالجة فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
closer to her home,
أقرب لبيتها,
and with a support group to help her cope.
ومع مجموعة مساندة لمساعدتها على مواجهة المرض.
Her story has a positive ending,
لقصتها نهاية إيجابية,
but there are thousands of others in similar situations
لكن هناك آلاف من الآخرين ممن يمرون بنفس هذه المواقف
who are much less fortunate.
وهم أقل منها حظا.
Although she may not know this,
على الرغم من أنها قد لا تعرف هذا,
my encounter with Celine has completely changed the way
لكن مقابلتي مع سيلين غيرت تمامًا الطريقة
in which I view HIV clinical trials in developing countries,
التي كنت أنظر بها للتجارب الإكلينيكية لفيروس نقص المناعة البشري في البلدان النامية,
and made me even more determined to be part of the movement
وجعلتني أكثر إصرارًا على أن أكون جزء من الحركة
to change the way in which things are done.
لأغير من الأسلوب الذي تتم به الأمور.
I believe that every single person
أؤمن بأن كل شخص
listening to me tonight can be part of that change.
يستمع إلي الليلة يستطيع أن يكون جزءًا من هذا التغيير.
If you are a researcher, I hold you
لو كنت باحثًا, فأنا أشجعك
to a higher standard of moral conscience,
على تبني معيار أعلى من الضمير الأخلاقي
to remain ethical in your research,
حتى تضل أخلاقياً في بحثك,
and not compromise human welfare in your search for answers.
وحتى لا تضحي بإفادة البشر خلال بحثك عن الإجابات.
If you work for a funding agency or pharmaceutical company,
إذا كنت تعمل في وكالة تمويل أو في شركة دوائية,
I challenge you to hold your employers
فأنا أتحداك أن تشجع أصحاب العمل
to fund research that is ethically sound.
على تمويل بحث سليم أخلاقيًا.
If you come from a developing country like myself,
إذا كنت تأتي من بلدة نامية مثلي,
I urge you to hold your government
فأنا أحثك على تشجيع حكومتك
to a more thorough review of the clinical trials
لإجراء مراجعة أخلاقية أكثر عمقًا للتجارب الإكلينيكية
which are authorized in your country.
التي يتم التصريح بها في بلدك.
Yes, there is a need for us to find a cure for HIV,
نعم, هناك حاجة لدينا لنجد علاجًا شافيُا لفيروس نقص المناعة البشري,
to find an effective vaccine for malaria,
لنجد لقاحًا فعالًا للملاريا,
to find a diagnostic tool that works for T.B.,
لنجد أداة تشخيصية لمرض السل,
but I believe that we owe it to those who willingly
لكني أعتقد أننا ندين للذين يوافقون بإرادتهم
and selflessly consent to participate in these clinical trials
وبغير أنانية بالمشاركة في هذه التجارب الإكلينيكية
to do this in a humane way.
أن نفعل ذلك بطريقة إنسانية.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.